<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>aws on Vladimir Varankin</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/aws/</link><description>Recent content in aws on Vladimir Varankin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/aws/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bookmarks (issue 7)</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/09/bookmarks-7/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/09/bookmarks-7/</guid><description>The complete history and strategy of Amazon.com and The complete history and strategy of AWS (Acquired podcast). In the world, where the growth of storages is massively outpacing the improvements in the speed of the Internet, a database is the most sticky technology. That&amp;rsquo;s how AWS locks the enterprises in: it’s impossible to migrate the enterprise-grade of data out of AWS (&amp;ldquo;It took thirty years for Amazon to migrate off Oracle to AWS&amp;rdquo;).
CMU Intro to Database systems / Fall 2022 (Carnegie Mellon University); PostgreSQL B-Tree index explained, pt. 1 (Qwertee).
Build a CQRS event store with Amazon DynamoDB (AWS).</description></item><item><title>Bookmarks (issue 1)</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/03/bookmarks-1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/03/bookmarks-1/</guid><description>Generics can make your Go code slower (PlanetScale):
boxing vs monomorphization vs partial monomorphization (&amp;ldquo;GCShape stenciling with Dictionaries&amp;rdquo;) interface inlining doesn&amp;rsquo;t work well with the 1.18&amp;rsquo;s compiler generics work well for byte sequences (string | []byte) in simple cases, generics can be useful for function callbacks. How Meta enables de-identified authentication at scale. The rational, the use-cases, and a high-level architecture of Meta&amp;rsquo;s Anonymous Credential Service (ACS).
Hidden dangers of duplicate key violations in PostgreSQL (AWS). INSERT … ON CONFLICT has additional benefits, if compared to relying on PostgreSQL&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;duplicate key violation&amp;rdquo; error:
no additional space needed for dead tuples less autovacuum required transaction IDs aren&amp;rsquo;t used for nothing, preventing (postponing) the potential trx-id wraparound. Diving into AWS IAM Roles for (Kubernetes) Service Accounts (IRSA).</description></item></channel></rss>