<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>rust on Vladimir Varankin</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/rust/</link><description>Recent content in rust on Vladimir Varankin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/rust/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bookmarks (issue 6)</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/08/bookmarks-6/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/08/bookmarks-6/</guid><description>Kubernetes antipatterns: CPU Limits. Always define CPU requests; never define CPU limits.
Explaining the unexplainable: buffers in PostgreSQL. Shared buffers are those, which&amp;rsquo;re&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;shared&amp;rdquo; between several DB sessions, i.e. data pages, indices, etc; local buffers, are &amp;ldquo;local&amp;rdquo; to a session, i.e. for temporal tables; temp buffers are for intermediate objects, i.e. when the DBMS does hashing and sorting.
Rust Iterator pattern with iter(), into_iter() and iter_mut() methods.
Standard iterator interface in Go (Ian Lance Taylor via GitHub Discussions).</description></item><item><title>Bookmarks (issue 3)</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/05/bookmarks-3/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/05/bookmarks-3/</guid><description>Rust tracks on Exercism. More than 100 coding exercises to learn Rust through practice.
PostgreSQL Anonymizer 1.0. A PostgreSQL extension for declarative data masking (docs and examples).
Queries in PostgreSQL: 4. Index scan (Postgres Pro). An in-depth overview of how PostgreSQL decides if it will use an index. One particular thing I had no idea about before I read the article was that &amp;ldquo;The Index Scan cost is highly dependent on the correlation between the physical order of the tuples on disk and the order in which the access method returns the IDs&amp;rdquo;. That explains several cases from my own experience, where postgres kept using &amp;ldquo;unexpected&amp;rdquo; sequential scans, after we added &amp;ldquo;another index&amp;rdquo; to the database.
Monarch: Google’s planet-scale in-memory time series database (Micah Lerner). A review of the paper (PDF), which describes the latest iteration of Google&amp;rsquo;s in-house metrics system.
Google’s API Improvement Proposals (AIP). A collection of design documents that summarize Google&amp;rsquo;s API design decisions.</description></item></channel></rss>