<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>English on Vladimir Varankin</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/english/</link><description>Recent content in English on Vladimir Varankin</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/english/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bookmarks (issue 4)</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/06/bookmarks-4/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/06/bookmarks-4/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tip.golang.org/doc/go1.19"&gt;Go 1.19beta1&lt;/a&gt;. As usual, lots of good improvements in the language&amp;rsquo;s runtime and the compiler, with one particularly interesting addition being the new &amp;ldquo;knob&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;runtime/debug.SetMemoryLimit&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.grammarly.com/blog/gender-neutral-language/"&gt;How to use gender-neutral language at work and in life&lt;/a&gt; (Grammarly). &amp;ldquo;Luckily, the English language is relatively gender-neutral in many respects&amp;rdquo; [at least, when compared to Russian and German languages].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2022/10092"&gt;Meet passkeys&lt;/a&gt; (Apple) and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mjHIt9lDBgA"&gt;Everything you want to know about WebAuthn&lt;/a&gt; (OktaDev). As you can guess, I&amp;rsquo;m very excited with Apple stepping onto the path to a passwordless future, while betting on WebAuthn standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2022/10077/"&gt;Replace CAPTCHAs with Private Access Tokens&lt;/a&gt; (Apple),
&lt;a href="https://www.fastly.com/blog/private-access-tokens-stepping-into-the-privacy-respecting-captcha-less"&gt;Private Access Tokens: stepping into the privacy-respecting, CAPTCHA-less future we were promised&lt;/a&gt; (Fastly),
&lt;a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/eliminating-captchas-on-iphones-and-macs-using-new-standard/"&gt;Private Access Tokens: eliminating CAPTCHAs on iPhones and Macs with open standards&lt;/a&gt; (Cloudflare).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Bookmarks (issue 2)</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/04/bookmarks-2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/04/bookmarks-2/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_object_identifier"&gt;Digital object identifier (DOI)&lt;/a&gt; (Wikipedia). A DOI is a persistent identifier or handle used to identify various objects uniquely. It aims to be &amp;ldquo;resolvable&amp;rdquo;, usually to some form of access to the information object to which the DOI refers. This is achieved by binding the DOI to metadata about the object, such as a URL. Thus, by being actionable and interoperable, a DOI differs from identifiers such as ISBNs, which aim only to identify their referents uniquely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://principledgraphql.com/operations"&gt;Operations principles: securely deploying the graph to production at scale&lt;/a&gt; (Principled GraphQL). Lots of things listed there apply to any sort of APIs — not only to GraphQL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dvb7ooaFJaU"&gt;Songs your English teacher will NEVER teach!&lt;/a&gt; (Learn English with Papa Teach Me). Vocabulary from &amp;ldquo;Savage&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;WAP&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;34+35&amp;rdquo;. This video is &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; not for kids!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.grammarly.com/blog/phrases-spring-clean/"&gt;8 phrases to spring-clean from your emails&lt;/a&gt; (Grammarly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.acquired.fm/episodes/platforms-and-power-with-hamilton-helmer-and-chenyi-shi"&gt;Platforms and Power&lt;/a&gt; (Acquired). &amp;ldquo;7 Powers&amp;rdquo; author Hamilton Helmer and Chenyi Shi (Strategy Capital), joined Acquired Podcast to discuss platform businesses, and how the &amp;ldquo;Power&amp;rdquo; framework applies to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@matryer/halfthings-a8c72365617c"&gt;Halfthings&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/matryer/"&gt;Mat Ryer&lt;/a&gt;).
Building something for the users to play with, to touch, to feel, to break, makes all the difference and moves the conversations away from the meta.
Doing &amp;ldquo;one thing&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;building an MVP&amp;rdquo; can easily pull you into a &amp;ldquo;too much&amp;rdquo; for a validation phase. Build a &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;halfthing&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; instead.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>