<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Dynamodb on Vladimir Varankin</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/dynamodb/</link><description>Recent content in Dynamodb on Vladimir Varankin</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/dynamodb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bookmarks (issue 5)</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/07/bookmarks-5/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/07/bookmarks-5/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/devinebass"&gt;Scott&amp;rsquo;s Bass Lessons&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/BassBuzz"&gt;BassBuzz&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube. I&amp;rsquo;m learning how to play bass guitar 🎸 now. So far, these two channels were the most helpful with both the practice lessons, and the inspiration to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/A_mstzRGfIE"&gt;Event-driven architecture done right&lt;/a&gt; (Tim Berglung, Devoxx Poland 2021). Try to learn what you&amp;rsquo;re trying to do, before you elaborate the architecture, if uncertainty is very high, and you don’t know exactly what businesses are asking. Just start with something (architecturally) simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/atc22-vig.pdf"&gt;Amazon DynamoDB: A Scalable, Predictably Performant, and Fully Managed NoSQL Database Service&lt;/a&gt; (whitepaper). &lt;a href="https://brooker.co.za/blog/2022/07/12/dynamodb.html"&gt;The analysis of the paper&lt;/a&gt; (Marc Brooker).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.acquired.fm/episodes/the-playbook-lessons-from-200-company-stories"&gt;Acquired&amp;rsquo;s lessons learned from 200 company stories&lt;/a&gt;: optimism always wins (Sony); nothing can stop the will to survive (Nvidia); it&amp;rsquo;s never too late (TSMC); focus on what makes your beer taste better (Amazon and all utility companies); don&amp;rsquo;t be talent — own the business (Oprah, Tail Swift); you’ll get the partners you ask for (Amazon&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;If you’re not on my bus, get off&amp;rdquo;), and more.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>