<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Berlin on Vladimir Varankin</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/berlin/</link><description>Recent content in Berlin on Vladimir Varankin</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/berlin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I've got COVID. What do I do next?</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/01/i-got-covid/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2022/01/i-got-covid/</guid><description>&lt;p>Go to &lt;a href="https://www.berlin.de/corona/massnahmen/abstands-und-hygieneregeln/">https://www.berlin.de/corona/massnahmen/abstands-und-hygieneregeln/&lt;/a> for the information (in German) about the latest regulations in Berlin. For the up-to-date information in your region, consult with your local authorities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Everything I list below are the steps I found relevant, after I&amp;rsquo;ve self-tested positive for COVID in Berlin, in the end of January 2022&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="friday-28th-january-2022">Friday, 28th January 2022&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I woke up with some &lt;em>mild&lt;/em> symptoms of cold. On the day before I worked from home, and only had a usual an hour-long walk around Prenzlauer Berg — Mitte after the workday. The rapid antigen test (&lt;em>Schnelltest&lt;/em>) was negative.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While still working from home, I took a &amp;ldquo;quiet Friday&amp;rdquo; at work, to simply focused on some mundane routines.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I went for a short walk in the afternoon, bought some grocery, and headed home.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="saturday-29th-january">Saturday, 29th January&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Didn&amp;rsquo;t feel anywhere better or worse: mostly had a runny nose and a dry throat. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to wait in the line for a quick-test, so I&amp;rsquo;ve just walked around the city for an hour and went home.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sunday-30th-january">Sunday, 30th January&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It felt the same as it&amp;rsquo;d been the day before, although the dry throat started to feel a bit more intense. Walked around for an hour, came home, made some coffee ;)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A couple hours later I started to cough. I made a self-test — we still had some at home — and,&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Here we are! Welcome to the &amp;ldquo;two-stripes&amp;rdquo; club&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Good coffee places in Berlin</title><link>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2021/10/good-coffee-places-in-berlin/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vladimir.varank.in/notes/2021/10/good-coffee-places-in-berlin/</guid><description>&lt;p>My definition of &amp;ldquo;good coffee places&amp;rdquo; includes, although, by no mean limited by, offering a &amp;ldquo;not too fruity&amp;rdquo; filter coffee or a decent americano.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>